Finding aid for the Caro Minasian collection of Armenian material Կարօ Մինասեան հայկական հավաքածու LSC.1632
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Persian letters and documents: Պարսկերէն լեզուով նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր:, 1604-1967; Series 5.
  - 5.5 Historical notes and documents: Պատմական ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1959
    This subseries contains notes and documents (including photographs and copies of some documents) on historical events and places, such as Bahman-Dez (DeŽ-e Bahman). Materials are in Persian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է ծանօթագրութի ւններ եւ փաստաթղթեր (ներառեալ փաստաթղթերի նկարներ եւ օրինակներ), որոնք պատմական դէպքերին եւ տեղերին (օրինակ՝ Բահման Դէզ) են վերաբերում: Նիւթերը պարսկերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Historical notes and documents: Պատմական ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1959 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - 5.6 Persian documents: Պարսկերէն փաստաթղթեր, 1604-1963
    This vast subseries contains documents primarily in the Persian language, with some Armenian, English, and Hebrew. Of special note are the Firmans (royal decrees) from various Shahs, and the antiquity of some of the materials. There are letters, title deeds, decrees, many business related documents and receipts, as well as other business and official documents. There are also two small, cloth satchels. Այս մեծածաւալ ենթակարգը պարունակում է գլխաւորապէս պարսկերէն լեզուով փաստաթղթեր, նաեւ մի քիչ հայերէն, անգլերէն, եւ եբրայերէն: Նշանակալից են զանազան Շահերի կողմից ֆարմանները (արքայական հրամանագրեր) եւ նիւթերի հնութիւնը: Կան նամակներ, կալուածագրեր, հրամանագրեր, շատ արեւտրին վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր, եւ այլ արեւտրական եւ պաշտօնական փաստաթղթեր: Նաեւ կան երկու փոքր պայուսակներ:
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1897 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1696-1776 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1716-1788 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1807-1880 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Documents (from Mr. Ara Yesaean): Փասթաթղթեր (Պրն. Արա Եսաեանից), 1843-1919 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Includes a Persian booklet published in 1899, May 1954-Isfahan
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1894-1931 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1910-1915 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Archives of Hessm Sulthan: Հէսսմ Սուլթանի արխիվը, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Decrees and title deeds: Հրամանագրեր եւ կալուածագրեր, 1795-1882 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Receipts and business related notes: Ստացագրեր եւ արեւտրական ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1894 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, 1908-1916 (Box 32, Folder 11)
      Includes a gray color cloth letter bag
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1809-1925 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Archives of Hessm Sulthan: Սուլթանի արխիւ, 1831-1833 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Archives of Hessm Sulthan: Հէսսմ Սուլթանի արխիւ, 1852-1878 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Documents belonging to George Mackertich: Գրիգոր Մկրտիչին պատկանող փաստաթղթեր, 1858-1861 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Bound copies of business letters: Կազմուած արեւտրական նամակներ (օրինակուած), 1878-1879 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փաստաթղթեր, 1880-1963 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, 1884-1907 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Decrees and title deeds: Հրամանագրեր եւ կալուածագրեր, 1893-1932 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, 1917-1941 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      Includes a green cloth bag for letters
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Business related documents: Առեւտրին վերաբերող փասթաթղթեր, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Hebrew document: Եբրայերէն փաստաթուղթ (Box 57, Folder 15)
    - Firmans (royal decrees): ֆարմաններ (արքայական հրամանագրեր) (Box 57, Folder 6-14)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, ca. 1600s-1700s (Box 58)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, undated (Box 59, Folder 3)
- Armenian Church Documents: Հայկական եկեղեցուն վերբերող փաստաթղթեր, 1623-1963; Series 6.
  This vast series contains materials issuing primarily from the Armenian Apostolic Church, including kondaks (pastoral letters), wills, title deeds, death certificates, records of donations, meeting proceedings, speeches, accounts, lists, correspondence, two paintings, and a scroll. Notable are the vast number of kondaks and the antiquity of many of the materials. Materials are in Armenian, with some Persian, English, and Dutch.
  Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայ եկեղեցու վերաբերող եւ պատկանող նիւթեր, ներառեալ կոնդակներ (եկեղեցական նամակներ), կտակներ, կալուածագրեր, մահուան վկայականներ, նուիրատուութեան արձանագրութիւններ, հանդիպումներին արձանագրութիւններ, խօսքեր, հաշիւներ, ցանկեր, նամակներ, երկու նկարչութիւններ, եւ մի հմայիլ: Նշանակալից են մեծածաւալ կոնդակները եւ նիւթերի հնութիւնը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են, նաեւ պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ հոլանդերէնով:
  - 6.1 Documents, Accounts, Lists: Փաստաթղթեր, Հաշուագրեր, Ցանկեր, 1623-1963
    This vast subseries contains documents, accounts, lists, correspondence, a scroll, and other materials largely connected with the Armenian Church. The documents include wills, title deeds, kondaks (pastoral letters), death certificates, records of donations, meeting proceedings, speeches, and other items. Of special note is a scroll recording gifts to churches and monasteries in New Julfa, and the name of the donors with their requests for prayers. Materials are primarily in Armenian, with some Persian, English, and Dutch. Այս մեծածաւալ ենթակարգը պարունակում է փաստաթղթեր, հաշիւներ, ցանկեր, նամակներ, մի հմայիլ, եւ այլ նիւթեր մեծ մասամբ հայկական Եկեղեցւոյ կապուած: Փաստաթղթերն են կտակներ, կալուածագրեր, կոնդակներ, մահուան վկայականներ, նուիրատուութ եան արձանագրութի ւններ, հանդիպումներ ին արձանագրութի ւններ, խօսքեր եւ այլ նիւթեր: Նշանակալից է հմայիը, որ արձանագրում է Նոր Ջուղայում եկեղեցիներին եւ մենաստանների ն նուիրատուութ իւնները ներառեալ նուիրատուն եւ իր աղոթքներին խնդրանքները: Նիւթերը մեծ մասամբ հայերէնով են, նաեւ պարսկերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ հոլանդերէնով:
    - Account booklet (wheat and grapes for Hakobos Tsayragoyn Vardapet) and Document: Յակոբոս Ծայրագոյն Վարդապետի ցորենի եւ խաղողի հաշուագիրը եւ փաստաթուղթ, 1832-1840 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Letters and Documents (Hovhannes Ark'episkopos): Նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Յովհաննէս Արքեպիսկոպոս), 1842-1858 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Receipts and letters: Ստացագրեր եւ նամակներ, 1850-1871 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Documents (Minas Hovsēp'ean): Փաստաթղթեր (Մինաս Յովսէփեան), 1852-1868 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Certificate of Testimony (for death of Ms. Hannayi Hayrapet Marut'ean): Վկայական (Տիկին Հաննայի Հայրապետ Մարութեանի մահուան համար), 1853 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Document pertaining to Armenian Clergy in New Julfa: Նոր Ջուղայի հայ քահանաներին վերաբերող փաստաթղթ, 1854 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Record of donations to Haykean Miabanut'iwn (Batavia): Նուիրատուութեան արձանագրութիւնը Հայկեան միաբանութիւն (Բթավիա), 1859 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Letter by T'addēos Ark'episkopos and Notice, Announcement, and Letters by Harut'iwn T'. Tēr Hovhaneants': Թադդէոս Արքեպիսկոպոսի նամակ եւ Ազդարարութիւն, ծանուցում, եւ նամակներ Յարութիւն Թ. Տէր Յովհանեանց կողմից, 1862 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Documents and accounts of T'addeos Ark'episkopos: Թադդէոս Արքեպիսկոպոսի փաստաթղթեր եւ հաշիւներ, 1862-1863 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Misellanous materials: Զանազան նիւթեր, 1863-1874 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Accounts, Lists, and Documents: Հաշիւներ, ցանկեր, եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1863-1894 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Documents of Movsēs Ark'episkopos: Մովսէս Արքեպիսկոպոսի փաստաթղթեր, 1864 -1868 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Documents and Accounts of the Armenian Apostolic Church, Calcutta: Կալկաթայի Հայոց Առաքելական Եկեղեցու հաշիւներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Կալկաթայում), 1865-1857 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Documents of Hovsep' K'ahanay Eliaz: Յովսէփ քահանայ Էլիազի փաստաթղթեր, 1866-1874 (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - Accounts and Notes: Հաշիւներ եւ ծանօթագրութիւններ, 1866-1876 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Letters: Նամակներ, 1863-1958 (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Letter of Tēr Grēgorios Tēr Eghiazarean regarding Volcano eruption in Batavia (Jakarta), Java: Տէր Գրէգորիոս Տէր Եղիազարեանի Բատաւիայում (Ջակարտայում) հրաբուխի վերաբերող նամակը, 27 August 1883 (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Christian Youth Association: Meeting Notes and Speeches: Քրիստոնեայ երիտասարդների միութիւն՝ հանդիպման ծանօթագրութիւններ եւ խօսքեր, 1889 (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - Booklet: "A gift of love at the grave of the deceased Father Srapion Paronean": Գրքոյկ` Նուէր սիրոյ առ դամբանս հանգուց եալ Հօր Սրապիոն Պարոնեանի, 1890 (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1813-1864 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Wills and other documents: Կտակներ եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր, 1814-1893 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Documents, Accounts, and Lists: Փաստաթղթեր, հաշիւներ եւ ցանկեր, 1825-1880 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      Includes excerpts from the Iliad handcopied in English.
    - Letters and documents: Նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր, 1827-1830 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      From Madras archives
    - Confirmation Card, Haykanoush George: Կնիքի քարտ՝ Հայկանուշ Գէւորգ, 1903 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1820s-1860s (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Weights measures: Կշիռք եւ չափք, 1880s (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - An address of welcome to the very reverend, the supreme Vardapiet Theodore Isaac, D.D. given by Mr. Mesrovb J. Seth, Calcutta: Բարի գալուստի խոսք Ծայրագոյն Վարդապետ Թէոդոր Իսահակին, ներկայացուել է Պրն. Մեսրոբ Ջ. Սեթեանի կողմից, 13 August 1933 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Documents (from Ter Karapet T'amikeanits'): Փաստաթղթեր (Տէր Կարապետ Թամիկեանից), 1830s (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Letters from the Ecclesiastical Council in Iran and India and Ejmiatsin: Նամակներ՝ Հոգեւոր Խորհուրդի Իրանում եւ Հնդկաստանում եւ Էջմիածնում, 1957-1958 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Wedding and engagement invitations: Հարսանեկան եւ նշանդրութեան հրաւէրներ, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Proceedings of the Iran-India Armenian Diocese's Representative of the 5th session: Արձանագրութիւն Իրանա- Հնդկաստանի Հայոցթեմի Պատգամաւորական 5-րդ նստաշրջանի, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Ledger, handwritten text for wedding service, sermon, and other materials: Հաշուագիր, պսակի արարողութեան ձեռագրուած գրութիւն, քարոզ եւ այլ նիւթեր, No date (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Text about Assyrians living near Lake Urmiah-Iran: Ուրմիա լճի մօտ ապրող Ասորիների մասին գրութիւն, No date (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Mkrtumean family: letters, documents, and miscellaneous materials: Մկրտումեան ընտանիք?` նամակներ, փաստաթղթեր, եւ զանազան նիւթեր, ca. 1830s-1880s (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Kondaks (Pastoral letters) and other documents: Կոնդակներ եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր, 1829 -1889 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Title Deeds and other documents: Կալուածագրեր եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր, 1748-1925 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1863-1869 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1735-1888 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Scroll listing donations to Armenian churches and monasteries in New Julfa and the name of the donors with requests for prayers: Հմայիլ, որ եկեղեցիներին եւ մենաստաններին նուիրատուութիւններ է արձանագրում ներառեալ նուիրատուն եւ իր աղոթքներին խնդրանքները, ca. 1623 (Box 53, Folder 4)
      The scroll measures 50" x 10". A note near the beginning reads: "թվ[ականի]ն ռհբ եղեւ սկիզբն բարեաց" (The year 1072 [1623] was the beginning of the good deeds)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, ca. 1720-1820 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1904-1921 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - 6.2 Kondaks: Կոնդակներ, 1693-1963
    This subseries contains mostly Kondaks (pastoral letters) from leaders of the Armenain Church. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը մեծ մասամբ պարունակում է հայ առաջնորդների կողմից ղրկուած կոնդակներ (եկեղեցական նամակներ): Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Kondaks (pastoral letters) of Matthew I Catholicos of Ejmiatsin and T'addēos Archbishop of New Julfa: Մատթէոս Ա Կաթողիկոսի եւ Թադդէոս Արքեպիսկոպոսի կոնդակներ, 1826-1863 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Kondaks of Movsēs Archbishop of New Julfa: Մովսէս Արքեպիսկոպոսի կոնդակներ, 1866-1870 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Kondaks of Grigoris Archbishop of New Julfa: Գրիգորիս Արքեպիսկոպոսի կոնդակներ, 1875-1883 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Kondaks of Makar Catholicos of Ejmiatsin: Մակար Ա կաթողիկոսի կոնդակ, 1889-1890 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Kondaks of Esayi Archbishop of New Julfa: Եսայի Արքեպիսկոպոսի կոնդակներ, 1891-1892 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Kondaks of Harutiwn Patriarch of Jerusalem: Յարութիւն Երուսաղէմի պատրիարքի կոնդակներ, 1892-1900 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Kondaks of Mkrtich Catholicos of Ejmiatsin: Մկրտիչ Կաթողիկոսի կոնդակներ, 1898-1904 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Liturgical readings from the book of Daniel: Դանիէլ գիրքից ծիսական ընթերցումներ, 1920 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Report from the delegate of Iran and India on the election of the Catholicos (Gēorg VI): Իրանա- Հնդկաստանի պատգամաւոր զեկուցումն Կաթողիկոսի ընտրութեան առթիւ (Գէորգ Զ), 1945 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Kondaks of Vazgēn I Catholicos of Ejmiatsin: Վազգէն Ա. կաթողիկոսի կոնդակներ, 1957-1958 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Kondak of Zareh I Catholicos of Cilicia: Զարեհ Ա կաթողիկոսի մեծի տանն կիլիկիոյ կոնդակ, 1958 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Kondak of Khorēn I Catholicos of Cilicia: Խորէն Ա կաթողիկոսի մեծի տանն կիլիկիոյ կոնդակ, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Kondaks (pastoral letters) of Gabriel, Patriarch of Jerusalem: Գաբրիէլ Պարտիարգի կոնդակներ, 1729-1758 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Kondaks (pastoral letters) and announcements of T'ēodoros Patriarch of Jerusalem, Gēorg IV Catholicos of Ejmiatsin, and Gēorg V Catholicos of Ejmiatsin: Թէոդորս Պատրիարգ Երուսաղէմի, Գէորգ Դ Կաթողիկոսի, եւ Գէորգ Ե Կաթողիկոսի կոնդակներ եւ ծանուցումներ, 1814-1924 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Kondaks (pastoral letters) of Archbishop Hovhannes Sureneants' of New Julfa: Արքեպիսկոպոս Յովհաննէս Սուրէնեանցի կոնդակներ, 1843-1845 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Copy of a kondak (pastoral letter) of Matthew I Catholicos of Ejmiatsin: Մատթէոս Ա Կաթողիկոսի կոնդակի պատճէն, 1859 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Letter from the Armenian monastics of The Church of Jesus Christ in New Julfa, Isfahan related to the complaints of priest Eznic: Ջուղայի Ամենափրկիչ Եկեղեցւոյ միաբաններու կողմից ղրկուած քահանայ Եզնիկի բողոքներու վերաբերեալ նամակ, 1693 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Kondaks (from Ejmiadzin): Կոնդակներ (Էջմիածնից), 1893-1909 (Box 57, Folder 2-3)
  - 6.3 Paintings: Նկարչութիւններ, 1692
    This subseries contains two paintings. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է երկու նկարչութիւնն եր:
    - Life of Saint Gregory the Illuminator: Ս. Գրիգոր Լուսաւորչի կեանքը, 1692 (Box 28, Folder 22)
      On parchment
    - Painting of Fathers of the Russian Orthodox Church: Ռուս Ուղղափառ Եկեղեցու Ս. Հայրերի նկարչութիւնը, No date (Box 28, Folder 23)
      On paper
- Armenian schools: Հայկական դպրոցներ, 1849-1949; Series 7.
  This series contains materials related to Armenian schools in Iran, and includes accounting and financial materials, topics of study, letters, announcements, school newspapers, school papers and other documents. Notable is a letter to the Shah concerning the teaching of Persian in Armenian schools. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, and English.
  Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Պարսկաստանում հայ դպրոցներուն վերաբերող նիւթեր, ներառեալ հաշիւներ եւ այլ արեւտրական նիւթեր, նամակներ, յայտարարութիւններ, ուսումի նիւթեր, դպրոցիթերթեր, դպրոիթղթեր եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր: Նշանակալից է Շահին ղրկուած հայ դպրոցներում պարսկերէն սորվեցնելու մասին մի նամակ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ անգլերէնով են:
  - 7.1 Accounting: Հաշուապահութիւն, 1888-1949
    This subseries contains accounts and account books relating to Armenian schools in Iran. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Պարսկաստանու մ հայ դպրոցների վերաբերող հաշիւներ եւ հաշուագրեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Accounting materials and book: Հաշիւներ եւ հաշուագիր, 1888-1925 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Accounting book: հաշուագիր, 1941-1949 (Box 27, Folder 13)
      English; M.J. Bumban, Imperial bank of Persia
  - 7.2 Armenian philanthropic Academy, Calcutta: Հայոց Մարդասիրական Ճեմարան, Կալկաթա, 1855-1907
    This subseries contains materials connected with the Armenian Philanthropic Academy of Calcutta, recording topics of study and graduated students, as well as letters and announcements. Materials are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայոց Մարդասիրական Ճեմարանի վերաբերող նիւթեր, ներառեալ ուսումի նիւթեր, աւարտուած աշակերտներ, նամակներ եւ յայտարարութի ւններ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Annual examination, topics studied and graduated students: Տարեկան քննութիւն, ուսումնասիրուած նիւթեր, եւ աւարտուած աշակերտներ, 1855-1885 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Announcements and letters: Յայտարարութիւններ եւ նամակներ, 1884-1907 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - 7.3 Board of Management, Armenian National Schools: Հոգաբարծութիւն կեդրոնական Գ. Քանանեան եւ Ս. Կատարինեան ազգային երկսեռ դպրոցներ, 1887-1945
    This subseries contains documents and account books related to the Board of Management for Armenian National Schools. Materials are in Armenian and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հոգաբարծութի ւն կեդրոնական Գ. Քանանեան եւ Ս. Կատարինեան ազգային երկսեռ դպրոցների վերաբեող փաստաթղթեր եւ հաշուագրեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Documents: փաստաթղթեր, 1887- 1945 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Accounting book: հաշւեգիրք, 1943-1944 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - 7.4 Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1849-1933
    This subseries contains a documents and papers connected with Armenian schools in Iran. Notable is a letter to the Shah concerning the teaching of Persian in Armenian schools, a lengthy report about the state of Armenian schools, information concerning curriculum and subjects taught, and the school papers and documents of Margaret Bamban. Materials are in Armenian, Persian, and English. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է պարսկաստանու մ հայ դպրոցների կապուած փաստաթղթեր եւթղթեր: Նշանակալից են Շահին ղրկուած հայ դպրոցներում պարսկերէն սորվեցնելու մասին նամակ, հայ դպրոցների մասին զեկուցում, ուսումի նիւթերի մասին տեղեկութիւն, եւ Մարգարիտ Բամբանի դպրոցական փաստաթղթեր եւթղթեր: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, պարսկերէնով, եւ անգլերէնով են:
    - Documents: Փաստաթղթեր, 1849-1933 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Margaret Bamban's school papers and documents: Մարգարիտ Բամբանի դպրոցականթղթերը, 1921-1929 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Report about Armenian Schools: Հայ դպրոցների մասին զեկուցում, 1932 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Letter to Shah regarding Persian language teaching in Armenian Schools: Հայ դպրոցներում պարսկերէն սորվեցնելու վերաբերող նամակ Շահի ուղարկուած, 1933 (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - List of furniture for Armenian College: աուցակ կահկարասքաց հայկական վարժարանի ընկերութեան, No date (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - 7.5 Newspapers: Օրաթերթեր, 1931
    This subseries contains a few editions of Armenian and English newspapers published by the students of the Stuart Memorial College in New Julfa (Isfahan), Iran. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Նոր Ջուղայի (Սպահանի), Պարսկաստանու մ Քօլէջի աշակերտների կողմից հրատարակուած թերթերը հայերէնով եւ անգլերէնով:
    - College Magpie: Մագփի Քօլէջ, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Manuk Newspaper: Մանուկ Ամսաթերթ, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 24)
- Armenian Communities of Iran: Հայկական գաղութները Պարսկաստանում, 1605-1962; Series 8.
  This series contains notes, letters, reports, newspaper clippings, lists, and other documents relating to Armenian communities in Persia. Notable are the inscriptions from gravestones in Madras, India, and the list of Armenian residents in Calcutta. Materials are in Armenian, English, and Persian.
  Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Պարսկաստանում հայ համայնքների վերաբերող ծանօթագրութիւններ, նամակներ, զեկուցումներ,թերթերի հատուածներ, ցանկեր, եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր: Նշանակալից են Մադրասի գերեզմանաքարերի արձանագրութիւնները եւ Կալկաթայի հայ բնակիչներիթիւը եւ ցուցակը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ պարսկերէնով են:
  - 8.01 Armenian folklore: Հայկական ժողովրդական մշակոյթ, 1947-1962
    This subseries contains folk poems and stories from the Armenian community of New Julfa (Isfahan), Iran. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Նոր Ջուղայի ժողովրդական բանաստեղծութ իւններ եւ առասպելներ: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Poems and Tales: Բանաստեղծութիւն եւ առասպելներ, 1907-1962 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Poems and Tales: Բանաստեղծութիւն եւ առասպելներ, 1957 (Box 35, Folder 5a)
  - 8.02 Armenian historical documents: Հայկական պատմական փաստաթղթեր, 1918-1919
    This subseries contains a few materials connected with famous Armenian personages: handwriting of Keri and documents connected with Van, as well as an announcement of General Torgom. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է համբաւաւոր մարդոց կապուած նիւթեր՝ Քեռիի ձեռագիրը եւ Վանին կապուած փաստաթղթեր նաեւ Գեներալ Թորգոմի մի յայտարարութի ւն:
    - Hand writing of K'eri and documents from or about Van: Քեռիի ձերագիրը եւ փաստաթղթեր Վանից կամ Վանի մասին, 1918 (Box 35, Folder 5b)
    - Announcement from General T'orgom: Գեներալ Թորգոմի յայտարարութիւն, 1919 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - 8.03 Armenians in India: Հայեր Հնդկաստանում, 1871-1949
    This subseries contains documents and papers relating to Armenian communities in India. Notable are the inscriptions from gravestones in Madras, India, and the list of Armenian residents in Calcutta. Materials are in Armenian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է հայ համայնքների Հնդկաստանում կապուածթուղթ եր եւ փաստաթղթեր: Նշանակալից են Մադրասի գերեզմանաքարերի արձանագրութի ւնները եւ Կալկաթայի հայ բնակիչներիթի ւը եւ ցուցակը: Նիւթերը հայերէնով են:
    - Number and list of Armenian residents in Calcuta: Կալկաթայի հայ բնակիչներիթիւ եւ ցուցակ, 1871 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Documents related to Armenians in Madras, India: Փաստաթղթեր Մադրասի հայերի մասին, 1935 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Inscriptions from Armenian Gravestones in Madras, India: Հայ գերեզմանոցի գերեզմանաքարերի արձանագրութիւնները Մադրասում, 1949 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - 8.04 Armenian villages in Iran: Հայկական գիւղեր Պարսկաստանում, 1839-1965
    This subseries contains material relating to Armenian communities in Iran, especially the regions of Charmahal and Peria, in the form of letters, reports, notes, newspaper clippings, lists, censuses, a map, and other documents. Materials are in Armenian, English, and Persian. Այս ենթակարգը պարունակում է Հայկական գիւղերին վերաբերող նիւթեր, մանաւանդ Չհարմահալում եւ Փերիայում: Նիւթերը նամակներ, զեկուցումներ, ծանօթագրութի ւններ,թերթի հատուածներ, ցանկեր, մարդահամարնե ր, մի քարտէզ եւ այլ փաստաթղթեր են: Նիւթերը հայերէնով, անգլերէնով, եւ պարսկերէնով են:
    - Correspondence of Martyros Ter Joakim regarding the villages of Charmahal and Peria: Տէր Մարտիրոս Տէր Յովակիմեանի նամակներ Չարմահալ եւ Փերիա գիւղերի մասին, 1839-1887 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - List of people and houses in different Armenian provinces: Հոգիների եւ տունների ցանկը տարբեր գաւառներում, 1900-1910 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Documents and letters pertaining to the Armenian village of Haykashēn (Isfahan): Հայկաշէն գիւղի վերաբերող նամակներ եւ փաստաթղթեր (Սպահան), 1918 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Reports, newspaper clippings, map, announcements, censuses, and other documents regarding the history of Peria and Chharmahal: Փերիայի եւ Չհարմահալի պատմութեան վերաբերող զեկուցումներ,թերթի հատուածներ, քարտէզ, յայտարարութիւններ, մարդահամարներ, եւ այլն, 1919-1965 (Box 35, Folder 13)